Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is קס"ח, Kuf Samech
Chet, 168. We are in shouting distance of the end of בבא
בתרא Bava Basra and we are dealing with the גמרא Gemara on
the משנה Mishna about the writing of different
documents—a loan document, a שובר, shovar, a receipt document, all other different
types of a כתובה, Kesuvah, a שטר אירוסין Shtar Erusin and whether,
you know, who under, for whom could it be written, you know,
without the other party
present? Obviously only the party that is obligating himself can be written
for him without the other party present, but not the reverse. Who
has to pay for the cost of the סופר sofer and so
on. Okay, we're in the middle of a discussion about the writing
of a שובר, shovar, of a receipt for the payment of a
כתובה. Kesuvah. So we pick up on the top of קס"ח עמוד
א' Kuf Samech Chet Amud Aleph and ההוא
תברא, Hahu Tavra, two lines from the top. ההוא תברא דהוה חתים
עליה רבי ירמיה בר אבא. Hahu Tavra dehavah chasim alei Rabbi Yirmiya
bar Abba. There was a certain שובר, shovar, you know, a receipt
that a woman would acknowledge payment of her כתובה, Kesuvah, that would
be that it was written that רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiya
bar Abba signed on it. אמרה ליה: Amra leh: לאו אנא הואי.
Lav ana havai. So she said to him, you know, this wasn't
me. This you signed this שובר shovar for that somebody's כתובה Kesuvah
was paid, the woman's
name on it, but that wasn't me who was part of that
transaction. So maybe somebody, my husband paid off to pretend that they
were me and that they had their כתובה Kesuvah paid.
אמר לה: Amar lah: איברא את הוית. Ivra, at havait. No,
in truth, I know it was you, don't think you're going to
pull this over on me. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: אף על גב
דסברי רבנן לאו אורחא למידק, Af al gav desovrei rabanan lav orcha
lemadak, even though we just said at the end of yesterday with
the case where, you know,
the same רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba thought it
wasn't the right woman and then he was reminded that it was,
and the גמרא Gemara says: Okay, you could have made that initial
mistake because you don't really look at women. Okay, so here, I
mean here it would seem obvious, here he was saying it is
you who I saw. So
תוספות Tosafos asks, if
you look at
תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says: כיון דדקדק. Kivan de-dikdak. ואם תאמר, Ve-im
Tomar, היכא דאמר מתחילה לאו היא היא, heichad-de-amar mitchila lav i hi,
אמר שיכול להחזיר, amar she-yachol lehachazir, if we said it yesterday that
when he initially thought it wasn't her he was going against the
testimony he wrote in the שטר shtar that he can retract that,
כל שכן כשמר מתחילה זו היא נאמן. Kal vachomer keshomar mitchila zu
hi ne'eman.
Of course if he says this is you he's believed, that's exactly
what it says in the שטר, shtar, כמה שכתוב בשטר. kemah she-kasuv
ba-shtar. אף על פי שאין דרכו להסתכל בהן. Af al pi she-ein
darko lehistakel ba-hen. So even though he doesn't normally look at women,
okay, but like what else would I think? He's saying what the
שטר shtar says. תירץ הכי קאמר: Tireitz hachi ka-amar: כיון דדקדק ואם
רוצה לחזור אינו חוזר ומגיד. kivan de-dikdak ve-im rotzeh lachzor eino chozer
umaggid. No,
what he's saying is that, you know, now even if you once
you said that you recognized her, you can't say afterwards you made
a mistake. All right, fine. Anyway, that was all pretty straightforward. אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, go back to the גמרא, Gemara, האי צורבא מרבנן
דאזל לקדושי איתתא, Hai tzurba merabanan de-azal lekadesh iteta, לקדושי איתתא, lekiddush
iteta, since we're talking about that תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim don't look
at women or pay close attention to women, so he says: Okay,
so if you're going to go get married, נדבר עם
הארץ בהדיה, nidbar am ha-aretz bahadeih, take somebody who's not a תלמיד
חכם, Talmid Chacham, somebody who's more familiar with the ways of the
world with you. דילמא מחלפו לה מיניה, dilma machlefu lah mineih, maybe
he will go ahead and they'll swap it on him so they'll
tell you they're marrying you this woman and then when it comes
to the חופה chuppah you're not actually looking at the woman you're
going to
marry and they'll swap it so the עם הארץ am ha-aretz will
be able to pay attention and say no they're actually giving you
some other woman as your wife.
So quite fascinating, this whole sociology that somebody would actually marry a
woman before really looking at her into the point of not even
recognizing her. Makes you sort of think of the פרשיות Parshiyos that
we're dealing with, רחל ולאה Rachel and Leah and how does that
happen and all of that. Okay, moving on. והבעל נותן שכר. Ve-ha-ba'al
nosein sachar. So now we
are continuing on and it says that the husband is the one
that will give the
שכר, sachar, that the husband is the one that pays for the
סופר sofer to write the גט. get. All right, so מאי טעמא,
mai ta'ama, what's the reason? דאמר קרא: de-amar kra: וכתב ונתן. ve-chasav
ve-natan. He has to write it and give it, so the סופר
sofer is doing it as his... שליח shaliach as his representative, so
if the סופר sofer is his agent, he should be the one
paying. You know, that determines who you're working for, the one who's
paying you. All right, ואידך דלא עבדינן הכי. veidach delo avdinan hachi.
So nowadays what's the explanation why we don't do that? Apparently, you
know, by the time of the גמרא, Gemara, the woman would pay
for the גט get to be written. שדיו רבנן אאשה כי היכי
דלא לשהייה. shadyu rabbanan a-isha ki heichi de-lo lishahai. The rabbis put
the responsibility on the wife so it shouldn't be an obstacle for
the husband, you know, it makes us think about all the עגונה
agunah cases. So if the woman is waiting to get a גט
get and
the husband is delaying because he doesn't have the money to pay
the
סופר, sofer, they figured, which is fascinating because sometimes the גמרא Gemara
assumes that a woman is not eager to get a גט get
and get divorced, but maybe once it's already in the process she
wants it done with. So if she pays it, it'll move things
along. Now again, I find it fascinating just thinking about the economics
and the dynamics and all of that, but also the question here
is of course how do they then deal with the fact that
he's supposed to be the agent of the husband? Is it a
type of, like,
הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beis din hefker and they assign the
money to the husband so they make it as if the husband
is paying? Not exactly clear how it addresses the whole sense of
that he's representing the husband. Okay, כותבין שטר ללוה אף על פי
שאין מלוה עמו. kossvin shtar le-loveh af pi she-ein malveh immo. You
go ahead and you again you write a שטר shtar for the
לוה, loveh, the borrower, even though the מלוה, malveh, the lender, is
not there because that שטר shtar is only obligating him. So if
he wants to carry that around in his pocket ready to give
to the מלוה, malveh, he's entitled to. And it ends by saying
that who pays for it, והלוה נותן שכר. vehaloveh noten sechar. The
one who borrows is the one that is paying for the סופר.
sofer. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obvious. You're the one
that's benefiting from this whole transaction, you're getting a loan and not
paying interest. So of course you're the one that's paying for the
סופר, sofer, for the costs. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. pshita.
Look, צריכא בעיסקא. tzricha be-iska. We're dealing in a case about a
sort of business investment. We've dealt with this in the past, something
that's like a half-loan, half פקדון. pikadon. You lend me money, I'm
going to go ahead and invest it. I'll keep some of the
profits, you'll keep some of the profits. So in that type of
a case both parties are benefiting. But even though both parties are
benefiting, the guy without the money is the guy who's more in
need and therefore he is the one that is seen as the
real beneficiary and he is going to pay for the cost of
the writing of the document, even though he doesn't have money. Okay,
כותבין שטר למוכר אף על פי שאין לוקח עמו. kossvin shtar le-mocher
af pi she-ein lokeiach immo. Similarly,
you can write a document for the person selling the property even
though the לוקח, lokeiach, the purchaser, isn't there because that's only going
to hurt him. Okay, and then it ends by saying והלוקח נותן
שכר. vehalokeiach noten sechar. The purchaser is the one that pays. That's
a good question. Who's benefiting in a case of a transaction, the
seller or the buyer? So the גמרא Gemara basically assumes, you know,
wasn't dealing with commercial transactions where you're like trying to sell as
many widgets as you can. It's dealing with, like, selling a property
and often it's, you know,
the plot of land you inherited or so on. So the גמרא
Gemara is going to assume that the general assumption is that the
purchaser is always the one benefiting. It's always a bad idea to
be selling, like, your property, again assuming you're not in commerce. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obvious. You know, obviously the
לוקח, lokeiach, the buyer, is the one that's paying for it, he's
the real beneficiary. לא צריכא במוכר שדהו מפני רעתה. lo tzricha bemocher
sadehu mipnei ra'assa. So here it says no, we're talking about a
case where yes it's your field, you know, you're selling your ancestral
field or something of that nature, but it's really bad, it's a
hardscrabble field and therefore it's, you know, you could sort of say
that you're lucky to unload it and maybe you're the beneficiary. And
nevertheless they make the לוקח, lokeiach, the buyer, pay. Why? Either because
even in that case they say anybody who buys land certainly is
in the better position, or a type of a לא פלוג. lo
plug. You know, once we're saying that the לוקח, lokeiach, the buyer,
pays for it, we're not going to distinguish between the cases. Okay,
אין כותבין שטרי אירוסין. ein kossvin shtarei eirusin. So it says you
don't you know, you don't write documents of like the אירוסין, eirusin,
like the תנאים tnayim about, you know, what each party is contributing
and so on, or נישואין nissuin which is likely the כתובה, ksuba,
okay, only when both parties are there because it's both parties are
entering the deal and they have to agree on the arrangements, there's
not one primary party there.
דחתן נותן שכר dechassan noten sechar and the groom is the one
that is paying. All right, he's seen as like I don't know
the primary, is it because he's seen as the primary beneficiary? Is
it because he's seen as the more active and initiating party?
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara
says פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious. Again, why is it obvious? Maybe at
the end of the day you're getting a wife, right, and you're
taking the responsibility in a patriarchal society. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. of having to support her and pay for her, so
even though you're getting a dowry and whatnot, you know, you know,
and even though you are taking those responsibilities to excuse me, I
said that wrong. Anyway, you're getting her, you're getting her dowry, yes,
it's true that you are taking on responsibilities and so on, but
you are still seen as the primary beneficiary. You're getting a wife.
Fascinating to think about how do you frame who's benefiting? So the
גמרא Gemara takes it so much for granted it says פשיטא, pshita,
obviously the groom pays. לא צריכא, lo tzericha, even if he's a
צורבא מרבנן, tzurba merabanan, even if he's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
דניחא ליה לחמוה לקרוביה, de'nichle ley l'chamuya le'kurvey, that the father-in-law is
going to really want him to have him as a relative. Oh,
I got such a wonderful תלמיד חכם talmid chacham as a son-in-law.
Nevertheless, we are fundamentally framing it that the groom is getting the
wife and he's the beneficiary.
All right, you can do a whole lot of sociological analysis on
all of this. Moving on. אין כותבין שטרי אריסות וקבלנות, ein kotvin
shtarei arisut ve'kablanut, so you don't write a document of like sharecropping
or of like a rental of a field except again it says
both of them have to agree because it's a two-sided transaction and
and and and והמקבל נותן שכר, v'hamikabel noten sechar,
the one who is the receiver, meaning the one who's getting the
field to work it either as a sharecropper or by paying rent,
he's the beneficiary. The other person sort of has the property, owns
the property, you're the person receiving it and getting the opportunity to
make a living, he's seen as the beneficiary. So the גמרא Gemara
says again, פשיטא, pshita, isn't that obvious? לא צריכא בבורא, lo tzericha
b'bora, we're talking about a case where you have to let it
lay fallow, you know, maybe for the first year or you have
to invest a lot in terms of fertilizing it and so on,
so you might consider yourself not really the beneficiary. Okay. אין כותבין
שטרי בירורין אלא מדעת שניהם. ein kotvin shtarei berurin ela m'da'at shneihem.
You only write a document of clarification with both parties
present. So the גמרא Gemara says what does that mean? מאי שטרי
בירורין, mai shtarei berurin, what does this mean? הכא תרגימו שטרי טענתא,
hacha targimu shtarei ta'anata, here in בבל Bavel it was explained a
document that lists the various claims and counterclaims that the litigants have
made in court. It's a record of what they have presented to
the judges. So it's a clarification of their positions. רבי ירמיה בר
אבא Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba אמר amar זה בורר לו אחד וזה
בורר לו אחד. ze borer lo echad v'ze borer lo echad. No,
it's in the process prior to the creating of the בית דין
Beit Din where each or it's the process of the creating of
the בית דין Beit Din before standing before the בית דין Beit
Din where each side picks one of the judges, we'll see this
in סנהדרין Sanhedrin and the two judges pick a third. So once
they have locked in their choices, you know, or made their choices,
we have to go into finalize it and get that written down
and that'll be the written record. Okay.
And it says there both parties pay because they're equal sides to
the litigant or to litigants or the court case. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says that you actually give each one
a copy of the document. You make two documents. So and each
one gets a copy. So let's see why.
So the גמרא Gemara says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר לשניהם כותבין
שנים לזה בפני עצמו ולזה בפני עצמו. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
l'shneyhem kotvin shnayim l'ze bifnei atzmo ul'ze bifnei atzmo. You write two,
each one gets their own. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא בכופין
על מידת סדום קמיפלגי. leima b'chofin al midat Sdom ka'miflegi. Let's say
the debate between Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים Chachamim is whether you
can impose force somebody not to take the position of מידת סדום.
midat Sdom. What's מידת סדום? midat Sdom? You know, that's שלי שלי
ושלך שלך. sheli sheli v'shelcha shelcha. Right? The משנה פרקי אבות, Mishna
Pirkei Avot, you know, it's מידה בינונית mida beinonit it's a normal
person, or it's מידת סדום. midat Sdom. You know, I keep mine,
you keep yours as opposed to any sense of generosity, that was
exactly the problem of סדום. Sdom. So can you sort of force
somebody to not take that position? Now how is this a case
of מידת סדום? midat Sdom?
So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it is you know like
here you have somebody will say look you keep your שטר shtar
and I want a שטר shtar for myself. Okay? I don't want
to pay for yours. I want one for myself. You keep yours,
I keep mine. That's a type of a מידת סדום. midat Sdom.
And we're going to say so, you know, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is going to say that's fine, you're entitled
to say that and to say you keep yours, I keep mine.
And the חכמים Chachamim say no, that's just wasteful and let them
both pay half rather than each one paying full and you know
and then you might have like you'll produce the שטר shtar when
the other one asks for it. Okay? So why should we go
ahead and indulge you that you want each person to pay full?
That's one way of saying it. And the גמרא Gemara says לא,
lo, no, that doesn't not necessarily the debate. I could say דכולי
עלמא כופין, d'kulei alma kofin, everybody would agree that you don't indulge
somebody who just סתם stam wants I keep mine, you keep yours
if there's a legitimate way that they can both share it. But
the question here is is there a legitimate way they can both
share it? והכא היינו טעמא דרבי שמעון. ve'hacha hinu ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל דאמר ליה לא ניחא לי דתהוי זכותך גבי
זכותי. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel de-amar lei lo nicha li de-tehevei zechutach
gabei zechuti. I don't want my rights to be with your rights.
I don't want you holding on to a document that is going
to sort of record, you know, my claims in court, if you
say that's what it was, right next to your claims. You'll be
able, when you're to inspect it, to be thinking about how you're
going to answer me back and so on. I don't want you
to be holding on to the record, the court record, while it's
still going on, you know, of the claims that I was making.
That's one way of understanding this. דדמית עלי כי ארי ארבא. de-damit
alai ke-ari arava. You're like a lion lying in wait, weighing in
wait, laying in wait.
So what's the solution? So according to this way of reading it,
the solution is you get a record of your claims, I keep
a record of my claims, so you're not looking at my claims
at the same time. The other version is no, the problem wasn't
that you're looking at the claims, but it's just that, you know,
you have control if you're holding onto the document. Yes, I could
ask for it from you, but you know you're holding onto it.
That's not fair. I want to always have immediate access, you know,
to the document. It's not true that we can equally share it.
All right, so let's take a look now at the next משנה.
mishnah. מי שפרע מקצת חובו והשליש את שטרו. Mi she-para mikzat chovo
ve-hishlish et shtaro.
Somebody paid off, he owed a thousand dollars, he paid off, I
don't know, 250, and now he owes the remaining 750. So what
they say is what he really needs is a receipt for the
250 he paid, but maybe the סופר sofer wasn't available, so they
said let's do the following.
Let's go ahead and give it to a third party who we
both respect, okay? ואם לא נתתי לך מכאן ועד יום פלוני תן
לו שטרו. ve-im lo natati lecha mikan ve-ad yom ploni ten lo
shtaro.
So I don't have a receipt, but I don't want you holding
on to the שטר shtar that says I owe you a thousand
dollars. Here's what we'll do: this guy, he's trusted to both of
us. He knows that I paid 250, and if I don't pay
you the balance by a certain date, he is empowered to go
ahead and give you back the שטר shtar and I'll have to
pay the full thousand. Okay, that's the deal that they made. הגיע
זמן ולא נתן, Higia zman ve-lo natan, and then lo and behold,
he wasn't able to give, to pay up the שטר. shtar. רבי
יוסי אומר ייתן. Rabbi Yossi omer yiten. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says this third party should do what the agreement was and give
the document, you know, back to the creditor, and you owe the
full debt. רבי יהודה אומר לא ייתן. Rabbi Yehuda omer lo yiten.
No, you don't. That was even though you said you were going
to do that, that promise does not bind you. And this, as
we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, is a classic example of אסמכתא.
asmachta. במאי קמיפלגי? Be-mai kamiflagi?
What's the debate? רבי יוסי סבר אסמכתא קניא. Rabbi Yossi savar asmachta
kanyia. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says that an אסמכתא asmachta is binding.
What's an אסמכתא? asmachta? So obviously huge discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim,
a lot of cases are labeled אסמכתא, asmachta, but generally it's understood
to be something that I am promising because I don't expect
the result to come about and I am sort of over-promising you
something that you don't deserve and I'm not really wanting to pay
it and it's not something you're really deserving, but it's because I
am so confident that it'll never come to that. Okay, so there's
not really in that case גמירת דעת. gemirat da'at. I don't really
want you to have it. I'm never expecting it's going to
happen and as I said it's not something like if it's logic,
you know, because of this I deserve to owe you the more.
So that type of accepting on myself this penalty that I don't
believe will ever happen, there's no real גמירת דעת gemirat da'at to
do it, so it's not binding. רבי יוסי סבר אסמכתא קניא. Rabbi
Yossi savar asmachta kanyia. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi said it is
binding. רבי יהודה סבר אסמכתא לא קניא, Rabbi Yehuda savar asmachta lo
kanyia, it's not binding. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר
רב הלכה כרבי יוסי. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar
Rav halachah ke-Rabbi Yossi. We rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Now
I should just mention that תוספות'ס Tosafot's גרסא girsa is אין הלכה
כרבי יוסי. ein halachah ke-Rabbi Yossi. Okay, so not at all clear
which way we're coming down. We'll go with our גרסא. girsa. We
rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that it is binding.
But it's not over. כי אתו לקמיה דרבי אמי, Ki atu lekamei
de-Rabbi Ami, when cases of אסמכתא asmachta came to רבי אמי, Rabbi
Ami, אמר להו וכי מאחר שרבי יוחנן מלמדנו פעם ראשונה ושנייה הלכה
כרבי יוסי. amar lehu ve-chi me-achar she-Rabbi Yochanan melamedenu pa'am rishonah u-sheniyah
halachah ke-Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan teaches us again and again
that we rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, that אסמכתא asmachta is
קניא. kanyia. So אני מה אעשה? ani mah e'eseh? What can I
do? I can't פסקן pasken otherwise. People maybe were hoping he would
פסקן pasken otherwise, he says no look, I have to follow רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אסמכתא asmachta
is קניא. kanyia. And then the גמרא Gemara ends ואין הלכה כרבי
יוסי, ve-ein halachah ke-Rabbi Yossi,
but we don't rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, אסמכתא asmachta is
not קניא. kanyia. Okay, so fascinating and then of course whole discussions
in תוספות Tosafot and the ראשונים. Rishonim. Does this mean אסמכתא asmachta
is never קונה? koneh? Maybe certain things are, certain things aren't. Major,
major discussion in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Okay, next משנה. mishnah. מי שנמחק
שטר חובו. Mi she-nimchak shtar chovo.
Now this actually happens in a case of כתובה. ketubah. You have
a document, it could be a כתובה, ketubah, it could be
a loan document, a promissory note, פלוני ploni owes me, ראובן Reuven
owes me a thousand dollars, and the ink is... is wearing away.
So maybe on the witnesses' signatures, maybe on the actual text itself,
by כתובות Kesuvos it often happens on the witnesses' signatures because they
sign with like ballpoint pen or whatever. Anyway, so I need a
replacement שטר. shtar. And I need a replacement שטר shtar from the
original date because the original date gives me liens from the original
date. I don't want a new שטר shtar to be written now.
So what am I going to do in order to make that
happen? So here's what the משנה Mishna says. מעמידו Ma'amido לאו lav
עדים, eidim,
you get witnesses there to see what's written in the שטר shtar
before it fades away so that they can testify that this loan
existed from this particular date. ובא U'ba לפני lifnei בית דין Beis
Din ועושים v'osim לו lo קיום. kiyum. And you come to בית
דין Beis Din and בית דין, Beis Din, the רשב"ם Rashbam says
it means the witnesses, but most ראשונים Rishonim say no, it means
the בית דין Beis Din sort of, you know, make essentially a
they establish the first שטר shtar based on the testimony of the
witnesses and they make a replacement שטר. shtar. And here's what they
write. איש Ish פלוני Ploni בן ben פלוני Ploni נמחק nimchak שטרו
shtaro ביום b'yom פלוני. Ploni. So and so's had a document of
$100, it got erased. ופלוני U'Ploni ופלוני u'Ploni עדיו eidav and, you
know, so and so are the witnesses. Now there's a question, who
are we referring to? Are we referring to the original witnesses? Well,
that's, you know, that's a problem because you also need to know
who's the second set of witnesses that are testifying to the original
witnesses because, you know, somebody might want to come and challenge them
or say or, you know, say they were lying, it's a fake,
whatever. So תוספות Tosafos says that פלוני Ploni ופלוני u'Ploni עדיו, eidav,
תוספות Tosafos claims means you're mentioning all the witnesses. So basically you're
saying essentially the following: like, you know,
לוי Levi ויהודה v'Yehuda came before us, the בית דין Beis Din
and testified that there was a document that, you know, that this
person, I don't know, אריה Aryeh had a document of a loan
of $1,000 dating January 1st,
2023, and ראובן Reuven ושמעון v'Shimon were the witnesses. So you mention
all the things that were in the document, who the original witnesses
are, and who the witnesses are that are claiming that that is
what they saw and you create a substitute document. Okay. In the
case of a כתובה Kesuvah there's actually a text, it's called a
כתובה דאירכסא Kesuvah d'Irkasa or כתובה דנמחקה. Kesuvah d'Nimchaka. A כתובה Kesuvah
that was lost or a כתובה Kesuvah that was erased and actually
it's exactly this, about creating a substitute כתובה. Kesuvah. So here, by
כתובה, Kesuvah, you know, nowadays we don't really worry so much about
the liens, but you need the כתובה. Kesuvah. But when you worry
about the liens, you really want to restore or get a substitute
for the original document and know the original date.
Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught:
איזו eizu קיומה, kiyuma, how do you write the, how does the
בית דין Beis Din sort of, you know, write in terms of
saying that we as the בית דין Beis Din received this testimony
and accepted it? So here's the language: במושב B'moshav תלתא tlasa הוינא,
havina, we were sitting in a convocation of three, we were, that's
the language of בית דין. Beis Din. אנו Anu פלוני Ploni ופלוני
u'Ploni ופלוני, u'Ploni, us, and then you list who the דיינים Dayanim
are.
And in that case, הוציא hotzi פלוני Ploni בן ben פלוני Ploni
שטר shtar מחוק machuk לפנינו. l'faneinu. Okay, this ראובן Reuven brought out
a promissory note that was erased ביום b'yom פלוני Ploni on this
and this date, ופלוני u'Ploni ופלוני u'Ploni עדיו eidav and, you know,
the witnesses were so and so, and either it was in the
process of being erased and we saw what it said and now
we're writing a substitute, or, you know, these other witnesses testified to
what was originally on it and now we're writing a substitute.
ונמצאת V'nimtzas עדותם eidusam מכוונת mechuvens גובה goveh ואינו v'eino צריך tzarich
להביא l'havi ראיה. raya. ואם V'im לאו, lav, צריך tzarich להביא l'havi
רא... Oops, I skipped a line. עדיו. ואם V'im כתוב kasuv בו
bo חקקנו huchkaknu לעדותן l'eduson של shel עדים eidim ונמצא v'nimtza עדותם
edusam מכוונת mechuvens גובה goveh ואינו v'eino צריך tzarich להביא l'havi ראיה.
raya. That, you know, if the בית דין Beis Din sort of,
you know, queried and inspected the witnesses, maybe it's the second witnesses
who saw what was in the שטר shtar or it was the
original witnesses, and we investigated it and we found that it was,
you know, that we could rely on it and so we knew
exactly what was in the שטר shtar either by second set of
testimony or the original
witnesses, then גובה goveh ואינו v'eino צריך tzarich להביא l'havi ראיה, raya,
you can use it to collect from the original liens, you can
create a substitute שטר, shtar, and you don't need any other proof.
ואם V'im לאו lav צריך tzarich להביא l'havi ראיה. raya. But if
you can't really prove what was in the original שטר, shtar, you
know, then you actually would have to, it's not good enough to
say oh it erased, how do we know you're telling the truth
or whatnot, you know, or even if we know there was a
loan, how do we know when the original date was and so
on, so if you can't prove it, you know, then he gotta
prove it. Okay. נקרע פסול, Nikra Pasul, if the, if a כתובה
Kesuvah is, or not כתובה, Kesuvah, a loan is, that it was
Okay. נקרע Nichra פסול, pasul, if a כתובה Ketubah or not כתובה,
Ketubah, a loan is not that it was erased, but actually it's
torn, okay, then it is invalid because the tearing might indicate that
it was paid. Somebody says, oh look, my promissory note is torn,
I need a substitute. Sorry, maybe the reason it's torn shows that
you paid it off. נתקרע Nitkarei however, torn on its own as
opposed to like clearly ripped, you know, by human hands, then כשר,
Kasher, then it's okay, and you know, we could write a substitute.
נמחק או נטשטש, Nimchak o nishtatash, if it got erased or it's
got smudgy, אם שמו ניכר כשר. im shemo nikar kasher. If you
can still see what the original text was and make out what
the original document said, then it remains כשר. Kasher. So now we
have to understand what's the difference between torn, you know, torn as
a way that creates a problem and torn by itself that isn't
a problem. היכי דמי נקרע היכי דמי נתקרע, Heichi dami nikra heichi
dami niskareia, what how do you what's the difference between those cases?
אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: נקרע קרע של בית דין. Nikra
kera shel Beis Din. Tearing that means that it's invalid is when
it's a particular way that a בית דין Beis Din would tear
a שטר Shtar to show that it's been paid. נתקרע קרע שאינו
בית דין, Nitkarei kera she-eino Beis Din,
when we say if it's ripped you can write a substitute, or
it's not invalid, that means that it was not clearly the way
a בית דין Beis Din tears a שטר. Shtar. Okay. How does
a בית דין Beis Din tear a שטר? Shtar?
So the גמרא Gemara says: היכי דמי קרע של בית דין, Heichi
dami kera shel Beis Din, what does what is the tearing of
a בית דין? Beis Din? אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: מקום
עדים ומקום הזמן ומקום התורף. Makom edim u'makom hazman u'makom hatorof. They
tear all the key portions of the שטר, Shtar, where the the
date, the amount of the money, and you know, all of the
sort of substantive part of the שטר, Shtar, the תורף. Torof. אביי
Abaye אמר amar שתי וערב. shesi v'eirev. No, you do a crisscross
cut. Okay, and this is also what they do when a כתובה
Ketubah is given and after it's received, you do a crisscross cut,
and that's very intentional, and that shows that it was done by
the court and the שטר Shtar is invalid.
Story. הנהו ארבאי, Hanu arvaei, there were these Arabs, דהוו אתו לפומבדיתא,
de-havu asu le-Pumbedisa, they came to פומבדיתא, Pumbedisa, דהוו קא אנצי אארעתא
דאינשי. de-havu ka-antsi a-arata de-inshei. Okay, that they would אנצי ארעתא דאינשי,
antsi arata de-inshei, they would force people to give them their land
and to hand over, you know, their their deeds to the land,
essentially. So these people wanted to protect themselves. So אתו מרי וסבייהו
asu marei v'savayu לקמיה lekamei דאביי. de-Abaye. So the owners of the
land came to אביי Abaye before they actually were anticipating they might
soon be compelled to give over their land and hand over the
deeds. ואמרי ליה: Ve'amrei lei: לחזי מר שטראי. lechzei mar shtarei. They
said let the master, אביי, Abaye, look, here's the document, here's our
deed, we legitimately own this. וליכתב לן מר שטרא אחרינא עליה. Velichtav
lan mar shtar achrina alei. And can you please write us a
duplicate document, דאם מנצית חד נתינן חד בידן. de-im mintsis chad netinan
chad biyadan. That if we're forced to give over our deed and
to to give it to these, you know, Arabs that are in,
you know, because we're being coerced, we will be able to still
prove that it's our land because we'll have this duplicate document. All
right, that sounds like a reasonable request. The only problem is, obviously,
it could be abused, because maybe they genuinely sold it to, you
know, to these people and made a lot of money, and now
they're going to claim it's theirs, or who knows, now that they
have two documents, forget these people that are coercing them, they'll sell
it to a to somebody else and take the money and then
they'll take out the other document and claim it's theirs. So אביי
Abaye did not want to do this. You know, he he could
maybe have sympathy or I don't know, not, for them, but it
was obviously, it was too, you know, given for abuse. So אמר
להו, Amar lehu, he said to them: מאי אביד לכון? mai avid
lachon? What can I do for you? I can't do anything to
help you. דאמר רב ספרא: De'amar Rav Safra: אין כותבין שני שטרות
על שדה אחת. ein kosvin shnei shtaros al sada achas. You cannot
write two deeds for the same field. דילמא טריף והדר טריף, dilma
teref v'hadar teref, because we're afraid that you are going to go
ahead and, you know, and collect and then collect again. So what
does that mean? So that's not exactly our case, but what that
means is if I bought a field from ראובן Reuven and then,
but I what part of the document basically said, if somebody comes
and takes this field away from me because he has liens on
it because of money he lent ראובן, Reuven, I am entitled to
get reimbursed from ראובן, Reuven, that was what the document said. Okay.
And now let's say I have two versions of that deed, you
know, a duplicate. Comes along somebody who ראובן Reuven owed money to
and takes the field from him from me, excuse me. I'm now
entitled to get reimbursed. I go to ראובן. Reuven. ראובן, Reuven, you
know, doesn't have the money. So now I go to other people
who bought other fields from ראובן Reuven to get my money paid
back. And I go and I take it from somebody and they
say fine, if I'm giving you the field, give me the שטר
Shtar because then I'm going to go also try to get reimbursed
from ראובן. Reuven. Anyway, give me your deeds which is evidence that
you have gotten be, you know, reimbursed from me. So I give
him the deed. And then טירפא. tirfa. I've collected my reimbursement from
that person who bought other land from ראובן. Reuven. Now I have
another deed and I'm going to go ahead and go to a
different person who bought land from ראובן Reuven and saying I haven't
yet been reimbursed and collect it from that person. So it's the
same basic idea. If you have two documents, deeds on the same
plot of land, you can abuse it because you can basically, you
know, sell it and then still claim you own it or in
a case of אחריות, achrayus, you know, collect twice because it was
taken from you. It's given to abuse. Okay. הוה קטרדי ליה Hava
katardy lay
so they were pressuring him to do something, אביי. Abaye. They weren't
happy with the answer. אמר ליה לספרי Amar lay le-safrey so he
said to his scribe, זיל כתוב להו הוא על המחק ועדים על
הנייר דפסול. Zil ktov lahu hu al ha-machak ve-edei al ha-niyar de-pasul.
So he said fine, listen, let's give them a document, but they
won't know better. We'll actually make it an invalid document. We'll write
the the deed that they're asking for on, you know, קלף klaf
that has been erased once and the witnesses on the bottom will
be on clean, unerased קלף. klaf. Okay, and as we've learned before,
that's invalid because of course you have to be suspicious that the
top stuff got erased and changed. Now this is obviously deeply disturbing
because just because people are pressuring you, you know, whatever, I mean
you would think that it's like actually a corruption of the court
of the integrity of the court to I mean to allow your,
you know, the scribe of the court to write a document that's
actually an invalid document.
You know, you would really think that that gets to issues of
זילותא דבי דינא, zilusa de-bei dina, the integrity of the court and
so on. I find this whole thing deeply disturbing. Besides that he's
deceiving them, but maybe he felt he had to get rid of
them. But anyway and they were giving him too much pressure. Anyway,
אמר ליה רב אחא בר מניומי לאביי, amar lay Rav Aha bar
Minyumi le-Abaye, so רב אחא בר מניומי Rav Aha bar Minyumi said
to אביי, Abaye, ודלמא משום ניכא ve-dilma mishum nika? ותניא נמחק או
ניטטש ומשום ניכא כשר. Ve-tanya nimhak o nitatash ve-mishum nika kasher. So
he thought, okay the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, that when
אביי Abaye said the first part will be על המחק, al ha-machak,
that you're actually going to erase a legitimate שטר shtar that exists
on the top and then you'll write theirs thing on top of
it. So he said one minute though if if that original שטר
shtar was erased maybe the outline of the you know the the
remnant of that is still visible and as our משנה Mishna teaches
if at least you can sort of see even if the black
isn't there but if you can see the lettering that remains then
the שטר shtar remains remains valid. So you're going to give them
a שטר shtar that at least what originally was written before it
was erased might still operate as a valid שטר. shtar. Okay and
maybe he thought you would actually first write the שטר shtar for
them for the deed, erase it and then write again on top
of it. So they'll say look it's actually a valid שטר. shtar.
Not because of the new stuff written, that's written on the מחק,
machak, but the original stuff is still legible.
So אמר ליה amar lay he said back, מי קאמינא שטר מעליא
אלף בית בעלמא קאמינא. mi kamina shtar ma'alya? Aleph-beis be-alma kamina. No
I didn't say that the thing you erase is a real שטר.
shtar. You know write out אלף בית גימל דלת הא, aleph beis
gimmel dalet hey, write some nonsense and then erase it and then
write this שטר shtar on top and the עדים eidim on the
bottom and the whole thing will be on clean background and the
whole thing will be invalid and that's how we're going to shut
them up. So again disturbing that he was going to give them
an invalid שטר shtar and deceive them that way. Okay.
Let's just look at this ברייתא, braisa, we'll start the ברייתא braisa
we'll continue it tomorrow. תנו רבנן הרי שבא ואמר אבד שטר חובי.
Tanu rabanan harei she-ba ve-amar avad shtar hovi. Somebody came and said
I've lost my promissory note. אף על פי שאמרו עדים אנו כתבנו
וחתמנו ונתנו לו אין כותבין לו את השטר. Af al pi she-amru
eidim anu kasavnu ve-hasamnu ve-nasatnu lo ein kotvin lo es ha-shtar. Even
though the witnesses said yes we were there, we wrote it, we
signed it, they're testifying to it, you do not write a replacement
שטר. shtar.
Why not? How is this different? You have the original witnesses. Why
can't you replace write it like you could in the משנה? Mishna?
Because here you don't have the original document. In the case of
the משנה Mishna you see the original document, you'll tear it up
and you'll write a replacement. Here the guy claims he lost the
שטר, shtar, but maybe he didn't and he's lying or maybe he
did but he'll find it. And similar to the point before about
two deeds, if you give him a replacement שטר shtar now he'll
be able to collect the loan twice because he'll pull out the
original one or find the original one. Okay, במה דברים אמורים, bamei
devarim amurim, when is this true? בשטרי הלואה, be-shtarei halva'ah, with promissory
notes for the reason we just said he'll collect twice. אבל שטרי
מקח וממכר כותבין חוץ מן האחריות שבו. Aval shtarei mekach u-mimkar kotvin
chutz min ha-achrayus she-bo.
However when it comes to writs of sale, so then you can
write as long as the second one does not have אחריות, achrayus,
does not have the ability to collect if the field is taken.
So this is really like the case we just did before. It's
two deeds on the same plot of land, but... But the גמרא
Gemara is going to say that but what the משנה Mishnah that
whatever the ברייתא Baraita just said, that it's written in a way
that he cannot collect twice reimbursement if the land is taken from
him.
Okay, that doesn't exactly explain if that's true then why in the
case before with the Arabs in פומבדיתא Pumbedita or whatever, didn't they
give them two deeds and the, you know, and the second one
just wouldn't have אחריות achrayus written into it. But here the גמרא
Gemara in contrast to what it sounded like before is saying you
can have two deeds of the plot of land or we're not,
you know, or we're not, it might wind up you have two
if it was lost and you found it, but as long as
the second one does not have אחריות achrayus we're not afraid that
you'll be able to collect twice if the land was taken from
you to be reimbursed. We'll talk about this more tomorrow. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer let's just get let's
just wrap this up and we'll continue tomorrow. אף בשטרי מקח וממכר
אין כותבין. Af beshtarei mekach umemkar ein koshvin. You can't even write
sort of bills of sale. Okay, and this is very complicated like
why? It has to do with the fact that for him, well
let's take a look. וכן היה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר הנותן
מתנה לחבירו והחזיר לו את השטר חזרה מתנתו. Vechein haya Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer hanosein matana lachaveiro vehachzir lo es hashtar chazra matanaso.
That if you go ahead and the שטר shtar and write a
bill of sale to somebody and then he returns to you the
document, the giving back of the document
reverses the original sale. וחכמים אומרים מתנתו קיימת Vachachamim omrim matanaso kayamas
it does not reverse the sale. So somehow because it reverses the
sale, right, what he is afraid of is that he says he
doesn't have his שטר. shtar. Why doesn't he have the שטר? shtar?
Because he gave it back to the original seller, maybe he got
paid for it, sold it back, the sale got reversed. Now you're
going to write a new שטר shtar and he's going to say
ah the sale didn't get reversed I always held onto it it's
still mine. Okay so we will see about this we'll unpack all
of this tomorrow.